[Brian Khuu] Welcome to Designing Open Democracy.
[Brian Khuu] I'm with Ben from Flux, and I will be your host, Brian Koo.
[Brian Khuu] So, Ben is a representative of the Victorian branch of Flux Party, which is a issue-based democracy party, which uses smartphone technology to help people have a more direct say in how the government should act.
[Brian Khuu] But before then, we actually met a guy from Flinders Street station, was it?
[Brian Khuu] Like, where was it again?
[Ben Ballingall] It was at federation Square.
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, we did down on federation Square, just before I met you for this.
[Brian Khuu] Yes, yes.
[Brian Khuu] And we met a guy named Owen, who like came from the UK.
[Brian Khuu] You remember?
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, well, you introduced me, you introduced him to me as a political refugee.
[Ben Ballingall] Of the Brexit.
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, but yeah, it was claimed to have left Britain due to the results of Brexit.
[Ben Ballingall] So, yeah, it was quite a spicy conversation to come into as a pro-digital democracy advocate or whatever I want to title myself as.
[Brian Khuu] Yeah, like I think the most important here is that it provides us with the introduction onto the background of where your party is trying to slide into, which is, for example, the UK had this issue of the referendum, which led to the Brexit, and his feeling was that it came as a total surprise to him and his left-leaning friends.
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, I love that it's, well, I don't love that, it makes me sad, but, you know, Brexit's definitely pointed to as this example of democracy.
[Ben Ballingall] But even in that chat, you know, I was talking with that guy, this is for quite a few years, you know, he's seen Brexit as this terrible example of democracy that went wrong.
[Ben Ballingall] But I guess getting to have a chat with him and, you know, even just bringing up that, you know, who made up the question?
[Ben Ballingall] What was the wording of the question?
[Ben Ballingall] Like, why wasn't, why did it take two years to implement?
[Ben Ballingall] Like, these are what people's real problems are, or, you know, at least it turned out in his case.
[Ben Ballingall] So yeah, it was just a good chat, because it's sad that Brexit is a negative for a lot of people.
[Brian Khuu] Yeah, yeah, and I think this led to a very good starting point of this loss of faith in democracy in general.
[Brian Khuu] And like, what do you feel led to this kind of loss of faith?
[Brian Khuu] And of course, we can then talk about, like, the issue based democracy that you're fighting.
[Ben Ballingall] That's a huge question there, Brian, right off the bat.
[Ben Ballingall] But yeah, I mean, it's something we got to with him.
[Ben Ballingall] There's so many facets to it.
[Ben Ballingall] It's how is the question asked?
[Ben Ballingall] Who's it asked?
[Ben Ballingall] What's the, you know, how are people incentivized to give an answer they truly believe in?
[Ben Ballingall] You know, like, you could look at Brexit again.
[Ben Ballingall] It's the first time people have had a referendum in decades.
[Ben Ballingall] How many people actually really, truly thought about the reaction and the result?
[Ben Ballingall] And how many people were like, Teehee!
[Brian Khuu] There was two events that I thought was quite interesting.
[Brian Khuu] For example, one of it was Boris Johnson, big red bus with a gigantic letters of how much it's going to cost to.
[Ben Ballingall] Sold to people comes in, yep.
[Brian Khuu] As well as...
[Brian Khuu] After the referendum, the biggest search was what is the EU?
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, exactly that.
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, exactly.
[Ben Ballingall] You know, what...
[Ben Ballingall?] Is it a true representation of democracy when the people who voted and took part in the vote didn't have a clue or didn't even really care or didn't even really know what they were voting on?
[Ben Ballingall?] Yeah, that's definitely is a takeaway from, at least from direct democracy as we think about it now, and something we're aiming to fix with Issue Based Direct Democracy, or we believe we fixed with Issue Based Direct Democracy.
[Brian Khuu] I will definitely follow up on that aspect.
[Brian Khuu] Before we start with that, like a couple of years ago, we had an event on citizen juries, and Nicholas Groen had this group, which I find quite interesting.
[Brian Khuu] What we're seeking for in the system is the well-considered opinion of the population.
[Brian Khuu] Is that what you're thinking of as well?
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, 100%.
[Ben Ballingall] I mean, we focus it through, I guess, the lens of specialization.
[Ben Ballingall] You want people who specialize in the question to be answering the question.
[Brian Khuu] I see.
[Brian Khuu] So yeah, now we can start actually getting to, if I remember, you said Flux is an Issue Based Direct Democracy.
[Brian Khuu] What is an Issue Based Democracy?
[Ben Ballingall] So, the philosophy we're calling Issue Based Direct Democracy is for what I call, I guess, a progression of a few of the thought processes around direct democracy.
[Ben Ballingall] So, it combines, obviously, direct democracy that we know, being able to vote yes or no.
[Ben Ballingall] But this comes with problems, which BIST has been discussing.
[Ben Ballingall] People have to vote yes or no.
[Ben Ballingall] They have to give a response.
[Ben Ballingall] They might not be informed about the subject or they might not care about it.
[Brian Khuu?] Also, in other countries, you don't have to vote, but in Australia, you have to vote.
[Brian Khuu?] So, maybe I should make this clear for those who are overseas.
[Brian Khuu?] In Australia, it is mandatory to vote.
[Ben Ballingall] Right, I'm talking about something different.
[Ben Ballingall] This would be direct democracy.
[Brian Khuu?] Direct democracy.
[Ben Ballingall] Not voting on politicians.
[Ben Ballingall] So, in a direct democracy, for instance, Brexit vote, you had to vote yes or no.
[Ben Ballingall] There was no option not to vote.
[Ben Ballingall] There was no option to do anything else with your vote.
[Ben Ballingall] So, this is where Flux comes in.
[Ben Ballingall] So, we're not just a direct democracy.
[Ben Ballingall] We've added in another element called liquid democracy.
[Brian Khuu?] Liquid democracy.
[Ben Ballingall] So, this is when you don't know about the subject, but you do think it should be dealt with by professionals or by insightful people or scientists or however, you know, a leader that you trust.
[Ben Ballingall] So, you can delegate on that one issue or in that one field to have someone else use your vote and tell you where it should go.
[Ben Ballingall] So, that's the second portion.
[Brian Khuu?] Where it should be directed to.
[Ben Ballingall] So, where it should be directed, you delegate to them, they move it on.
[Ben Ballingall] So, this cleans up a lot of the problems with direct democracy, but it also brings in, I guess, a few extra problems in that there's the hubris.
[Ben Ballingall] People are just going to keep going to the same leader when it's not necessarily the best idea.
[Brian Khuu] Is that kind of related to the tribal effect that we're seeing?
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah.
[Ben Ballingall] I mean, it'd be a much smaller version right now.
[Ben Ballingall] We see it in the whole party, but you'd still go, you know, Dr. Carl is my science and tech guy, and he always will be for the next 20 years, because I know him, but he might not still have the best ideas.
[Ben Ballingall] So what you actually want is a way for people to specialise and hyper specialise in their skills.
[Ben Ballingall] So the other addition, apart from liquid democracy, is the ability in a vote where none of the answers are any good to you.
[Ben Ballingall] The addition, the ability to not vote at all, and abstain from voting, and then you would store up a little bit of that vote's energy, and then you can put it towards your own novel idea, or something you're really, really passionate about.
[Ben Ballingall] Because yeah, we don't want, we also want a reward.
[Ben Ballingall] We don't want to incentivise people just giving away their vote.
[Ben Ballingall] obviously, liquid democracy is easier, but it might not be the best answer for you.
[Brian Khuu] So in other words, it sounds like you're almost trying to, like, get people to abstain from certain issues if they are not passionate enough about that particular issue.
[Ben Ballingall?] A hundred percent.
[Brian Khuu] Like I remembered, you made an analogy between those who are Christian, and those who are atheists, and in regard to, say, the abortion debate, if everybody has the same amount of vote, they may not choose to vote in a way that is suitable for the entire nation, but instead you want to get them to actually make a decision of what they care more about.
[Brian Khuu] Maybe they care more about religious right rather than banning abortion completely.
[Brian Khuu] So maybe you could tell me a bit more in your words.
[Brian Khuu] Is that the angle?
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, I don't remember the specific analogy, but I'll pick it up.
[Ben Ballingall] I think it's that the, yeah, you know, it's, or even the alternative of maybe you believe in every single Christian value except for being anti-abortion.
[Ben Ballingall] So even taking it from the other side, and then it's like, you would have to be right now, if you wanted to have support for all of your other 49 values, you have to, by default, support that other one.
[Ben Ballingall] And that's not necessarily what we want, because that might, you might not truly view that as the best, you know, let's say Christian values, sticky one to stay with, but let's go with it.
[Ben Ballingall] You know, Christian values of kindness and humility and being kind to others, you might see them being upheld in every other way, except for this one.
[Brian Khuu] So it's kind of like similar to having to choose a cable TV packaging, but like a lot of them forces you to also choose.
[Ben Ballingall] Hey, there's an analogy I feel much safer going into.
[Ben Ballingall] Yes, exactly.
[Ben Ballingall] And this is, oh, that makes me feel so much better.
[Ben Ballingall] Right now in your voting, you could specialize just in the sporting package.
[Brian Khuu?] Yes.
[Ben Ballingall] And you would be...
[Ben Ballingall] Everybody wants the sport.
[Ben Ballingall] You just want that sports package.
[Ben Ballingall] You don't care about anything else.
[Ben Ballingall] And you would be rewarded by, instead of saving money for not buying those other packages, you would be rewarded by getting more political energy that you can spend on sports related things.
[Ben Ballingall] I like that.
[Ben Ballingall] Oh, thank you for giving me that analogy rather than me tiptoeing through Christian values.
[Ben Ballingall] But yeah, that's a really great analogy though.
[Brian Khuu] Okay, so I think now you explained a bit more about Issue Based Democracy, and so the audience will at least know what IBDD stands for.
[Brian Khuu] But there's also this other model which you would have heard of quite a bit, and I've mentioned not too long ago, about Citizen Juries.
[Brian Khuu] And Flux, on the other hand, implements IBDD.
[Brian Khuu] So I'm kind of curious, why didn't Flux use Citizen Juries?
[Brian Khuu] Why IBDD?
[Ben Ballingall] I'm laughing about this because I was jokingly being a little rough on Citizen Juries.
[Ben Ballingall] So Citizen Juries and IBDD, I think come from the same place in that they're both trying to fix bad representation.
[Ben Ballingall] They don't want us to be represented poorly by people who aren't us, the people.
[Ben Ballingall] So in that way, I think Citizen Juries are really great.
[Ben Ballingall] They empower ordinary people who are interested and don't actually want to see the change happen.
[Ben Ballingall] But what they don't do is they don't reward specialization, and they don't reward someone getting the correct answer.
[Ben Ballingall] Someone doing really well in a Citizen Jury may never be called up again.
[Ben Ballingall] And that's something Flux wants to limit with IBDD.
[Ben Ballingall] So we focus on-
[Brian Khuu] It's kind of similar to how you notice with the modern day society, everybody is starting to hyper specialize in their own engineering, doctors, fields and so on.
[Ben Ballingall] Yes, that's almost perfectly it.
[Ben Ballingall] If everybody's specializing in their fields, we want to reward that.
[Ben Ballingall] We don't want to try and create these representatives that are really great at most things, or jack of all trades at most things, when we could have masters at everything, delivering the results that are given to, you know, that are confirmed by the people, as opposed to...
[Brian Khuu] So, maybe the other analogy you could probably make as well is the pattern system, and how a lot of the issue with the pattern system is that those that do the revoke of the pattern systems are not always the same people that are specialized in understanding how it works, especially when you put it to the jury system.
[Ben Ballingall] What do you mean?
[Brian Khuu] At the moment, if I understand, when you have pattern conflicts, people need to call up experts to talk to the juries, but a lot of the issues is that the juries, in a very short amount of time, have to pick up the network stack, all sorts, computer theory, etc.
[Brian Khuu] And this can, in some ways, overwhelm the jury system in trying to deal with making the right choices of who to order pattern to, or whether the pattern is valid or not.
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, I think so.
[Ben Ballingall] And I think it's like...
[Brian Khuu] And I think this ties into the aspects of what you're trying to say about the need for hyper-specialization on maybe even on the complex issues.
[Ben Ballingall] Yes, that's exactly it.
[Ben Ballingall] It's like, you know, you could...
[Ben Ballingall] You can hope that, especially in this patent case, you can hope that a jury will be able to see the just thing to do.
[Ben Ballingall] And, you know, they might be...
[Ben Ballingall] If someone can explain it to them correctly, they can make the correct decision because they have less...
[Ben Ballingall] You know, they don't get...
[Ben Ballingall] They have no dog in the fight, so they're going to make the correct decision because that is their task as the jury.
[Ben Ballingall] But you're adding in the fact that they know that they can be bamboozled or just jargoned until they don't actually know what they're looking at, whereas that's something you could never get...
[Ben Ballingall] You couldn't do to a specialist.
[Ben Ballingall] So instead of having that jury, you have a specialist everybody trusts, and they can't be bamboozled, hopefully.
[Brian Khuu] Of course, the biggest issue is that we delegate and our trust to a politician.
[Brian Khuu] What's not to say that this isn't going to happen as well with those we delegate our trust to?
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, that is, like I was saying, a flaw in liquid democracy that used the term hubris.
[Ben Ballingall] But also that...
[Brian Khuu] Liquid democracy, IBDD?
[Ben Ballingall] Yes, it's within IBDD.
[Brian Khuu] Oh, within IBDD.
[Ben Ballingall] So that's a problem.
[Ben Ballingall] It is great that you can delegate to someone, but they can either get lazy or they can be corrupted.
[Ben Ballingall] The best thing about IB or within a digital liquid democracy is the second they do that, you pull that power back.
[Brian Khuu] I see.
[Brian Khuu] So there's a accountability feedback loop that you're saying that is missing from the original.
[Brian Khuu] Liquid democracy that was applied by the Pirate Party of another country, if I remember.
[Brian Khuu] They tried to test it, but pure liquid democracy, but they had a bit of issue that you were talking about.
[Brian Khuu] Yeah, actually.
[Brian Khuu] What would you say in this IBDD, Issue Based Direct Democracy is an evolution of liquid democracy?
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah.
[Ben Ballingall] evolutions, maybe not the term I'd use, just liquid democracy is just one facet within IBDD that serves a purpose.
[Ben Ballingall] It serves the purpose to remove the staticness of direct democracy, and make it a bit more fluid, and make it sure that people who care and people who want to help can be empowered.
[Ben Ballingall] But it's not so much an evolution in that it's a logical progression of...
[Brian Khuu?] progression.
[Ben Ballingall] Because they serve separate purposes, and the three keys, direct democracy, liquid democracy, and the issue based vote sharing, they all serve different purposes.
[Ben Ballingall] They're not necessarily like a linear thing.
[Brian Khuu] I think that's pretty sensible.
[Brian Khuu] So people are unengaged.
[Brian Khuu] They're not aware that they're not in a democracy.
[Brian Khuu] The media doesn't tell them the choices.
[Brian Khuu] Even if I like this whole concept of the Flux IPDD system, how do you get people to use it if they're not aware of this system, or could find it difficult to understand it?
[Ben Ballingall] It's a difficult one.
[Ben Ballingall] I mean, obviously, we're looking at the most straightforward thing.
[Ben Ballingall] Get a member represented.
[Ben Ballingall] An elected and a representative into parliament.
[Ben Ballingall] So obviously, election campaigns and running successful ones of those are the black and white answer to that question.
[Ben Ballingall] That's our hope.
[Ben Ballingall] That's our goal for it all.
[Ben Ballingall] Secondary to that would be we're hoping to release an app that allows people to mirror parliament and have their vote and then have it displayed according to their community.
[Ben Ballingall] And we're hoping that that as a method of people lobbying their representatives and the idea could really catch on.
[Ben Ballingall] The idea that what's happening in parliament, I'll have a look, I'll vote on it and I'll push it to my friends and more importantly my MP.
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, that's the stepping stone to getting to people that are really interested.
[Ben Ballingall] I certainly hope it does.
[Brian Khuu] So, well, once you do get it in, like every kind of curious to know about the algorithms and like, how would these issues be selected?
[Brian Khuu] Like as representative as possible.
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah.
[Ben Ballingall] So initially, I imagine with one MP, a lot of the time we're just straight reacting to other parties, and we're allowing every person in our electorate to vote yes or no, to what other political parties want.
[Ben Ballingall] But what you can do with when you elect not to vote on things in that parliament, you store up that energy and then you can put that up into like, I guess, a separate voting mechanism in the flux ecosystem.
[Ben Ballingall] So yeah, you could renege from making up these numbers, but 50 votes and that should afford you enough to be able to put forward a piece of legislation that you yourself can write up.
[Ben Ballingall] And then yeah, everyone can vote on that from just within your community.
[Brian Khuu] Nice, nice.
[Brian Khuu] What is the theory and the philosophy behind IBDD and flux?
[Brian Khuu] So we now explored citizen juries and flux, but I'd be curious to know between flux and IBDD, like how, what is the relation of IBDD to flux?
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, flux, so IBDD is the democratic model that flux the political party uses.
[Ben Ballingall] So IBDD is just a voting system.
[Ben Ballingall] So in that regard, it only, I guess, it only touches on the legislative arm of government, parliament, MPs voting on things.
[Ben Ballingall] That would be what IBDD does.
[Ben Ballingall] As opposed to what flux does.
[Ben Ballingall] Flux is a political apparatus.
[Ben Ballingall] It's going to put MPs into parliament, who obviously, they vote.
[Ben Ballingall] They vote according to IBDD.
[Ben Ballingall] But they also have to look into, you know, how do we make government transparent, as transparent as possible, that's safe, so that we're giving people the information so they can make the right decisions.
[Ben Ballingall] And they're, but you know, we're not maybe giving away enough that we could damage national security or commerce, which will be a lot of what we're doing, actually technically, you know, also following up other parties and making sure where their information comes from, making sure that's transparent.
[Ben Ballingall] That would be a lot of, you know, flux as a political party and actor, not related to our democratic system that we use.
[Brian Khuu] So about the interest groups, like part of the concern that a lot of people have been talking to me is about, like parties are doing things in the interests of big donors, and they're gaming the systems.
[Brian Khuu] How would you stop this in your proposal?
[Brian Khuu] Like...
[Ben Ballingall] That's one of the best things about the blockchain technology we use.
[Ben Ballingall] It gives a full ledger that shows every single vote.
[Ben Ballingall] obviously, these votes are anonymized, so you can't actually link them to a human, a person, and find their house.
[Ben Ballingall] But you can rest assured that it is one person that took that vote.
[Ben Ballingall] So this means as long as we, as a party and as MPs, as long as we stick to literally one rule, we vote how the app says, we can't actually be corrupted by the usual, you know, here's a briefcase full of money, vote no.
[Ben Ballingall] And if we do, everyone will know at that one second, and then we're dead in the water.
[Ben Ballingall] So it means that if these big companies and stuff do want to manipulate people, or manipulate the political process, they actually have to manipulate the entire community.
[Brian Khuu?] I see.
[Ben Ballingall] So now you're looking at, you know, they have to do mass media or a mass information campaign, which for them is going to be incredibly expensive that it can't be manipulative or based on a lie.
[Brian Khuu?] And that's the current issue right now.
[Brian Khuu?] There's a lot of people concerned with the concentration of media, if I remember.
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah.
[Ben Ballingall] So it's, you know, it's like, we can't storm in and say that we're going to destroy Murdoch and only use this open-source internet-based media system.
[Ben Ballingall] Like, that's not how to level, or it might work eventually like that, but that's not how it works nowadays.
[Ben Ballingall] But what it does do is it means that these parties and these financial backers have to get the voting of the people.
[Ben Ballingall] And to do that, they have to inform them.
[Ben Ballingall] And if they lie, they lose our trust forever, and they just blew $8 million on an advertising campaign.
[Ben Ballingall] So it would be better for them not to lie.
[Ben Ballingall] And to give an idea that doesn't suck.
[Brian Khuu] I do remember in our last election in 2019, Clive Palmer dropped the money.
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, put $90 million down or something.
[Brian Khuu?] I think it dropped, was it nearly $60 million on advertising?
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, something like that.
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, can't remember.
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, for sure.
[Ben Ballingall] But yeah, exactly.
[Ben Ballingall] And it's like, and what's worse is, people point to that as like, Clive Palmer did that, but if you remember his ads, they were idiotic.
[Ben Ballingall] They gave you nothing.
[Ben Ballingall] They were just like, Australia, yeah?
[Ben Ballingall] If he wanted to blow $60 million to affect one issue, it's not gonna work just being like, vote yes.
[Ben Ballingall] It would actually require, inform me why I should vote yes, because Dave on his couch just did a live video on YouTube for free, and it explained why I should vote no.
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, so that's what I think.
[Ben Ballingall] It's like, you can't destroy money wanting to affect politics, but you can make a system where it's stupidly expensive to try and lie, and you have to be transparent to the people.
[Ben Ballingall] That's what we're going for.
[Brian Khuu] That's quite interesting.
[Brian Khuu] So like, for the audience who listen to your theory and understand the idea and actually accept and want to see this happen, like some of the consensus would have in terms of the implementation is, if you manage to get a representative into parliament, how is it going to work with the normal system that we've got?
[Brian Khuu] And there are soon to be autonomous actors, so couldn't they just vote the way they want against the wish of flux?
[Ben Ballingall] Yes.
[Ben Ballingall] That's the longer short of it.
[Ben Ballingall] It's...
[Ben Ballingall] So if we think of normal party politics, and this ability for a parliamentarian to always be able to vote however they want, it's actually a really nice thing.
[Ben Ballingall] When you think about normal politics, it means that the liberals can't go sign this contract that says you'll vote how I tell you, or you owe me $10 million.
[Ben Ballingall] They can't do that sort of thing, or you'll go to jail if you're the government.
[Ben Ballingall] Without this protection, that sort of thing could happen.
[Ben Ballingall] So it's actually a good thing.
[Ben Ballingall] When it comes to representing the people, it's a negative, obviously.
[Ben Ballingall] I believe these people, an MP, could openly go against the people's voting.
[Ben Ballingall] However, if they did that, then they're not able to ever come back.
[Ben Ballingall] You know, you can vote against the Liberal Party and then be like, oh, I just disagreed on that one, but I agree with the rest, I'm back.
[Ben Ballingall] Or you can just sit as an independent and still pretend you're holding up the values that you said you would at the start.
[Ben Ballingall] So it's kind of like how you don't really see members of one political party switch to the other and then switch back.
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, it's, I mean, what have we got?
[Ben Ballingall] We've got, you know, Corey Bernardi's, one of them, I think Santafond did it as well, but you know, these people that, they're able to backstab their party and not vote how the party wanted, which is the only thing they agreed that they would do and why they got elected, because they're able to go, oh, the party has changed, or the party's views changed from mine.
[Ben Ballingall] Whereas if you're a Flux representative, the only thing you're ever holding is that you'll do what the people say.
[Ben Ballingall] So to go against that, you have to be like, I believe I'm smarter than the people.
[Ben Ballingall] And you're just dead in, you know, you've just ruined yourself.
[Brian Khuu] Maybe I should phrase it a bit more of what you say is that, isn't it more that I no longer believe in the system that you run?
[Brian Khuu] Because like, of course, every party says is, I believe in the will of the public.
[Brian Khuu] But essentially, if you're part of the flux, I think the theory here is that you believe in the strength and accuracy of the flux system, so you will vote with it.
[Brian Khuu] But if you're voting against it, then in some ways you're saying that you lost trust.
[Ben Ballingall] Exactly, it's something where, like I'm not gonna lie, if someone did that, it would look shit.
[Ben Ballingall] It would look terrible for us as flux.
[Ben Ballingall] But it wouldn't kill flux.
[Ben Ballingall] It wouldn't kill the idea of being represented by the community voting.
[Ben Ballingall] It would just ruin that person.
[Ben Ballingall] It would say they don't trust the people.
[Ben Ballingall] It doesn't ruin that voting can happen, and that's how we should be represented.
[Ben Ballingall] So it'd be sad, but it's not a death knell for us.
[Brian Khuu] Okay, so what kind of results do you need to see in the next election before you could get a representative in parliament to demonstrate this kind of system?
[Brian Khuu] Because we have had an election last year, so it's going to be a kind of a few years ahead.
[Brian Khuu] But it'd be interesting to know what ideas have been, what it's going to take.
[Ben Ballingall] Yeah, for sure.
[Ben Ballingall] It's, what, I can't remember percentages, unfortunately, right now, but I'm going to make them up.
[Ben Ballingall] So we just got out of a federal election where, you know, when you look at Senate writings and preference slides and things like that, I believe it was possible with about 4% of the vote for us to get someone elected, you know, in a lower Senate seat.
[Ben Ballingall] It'd be very, very unlikely for us ever to get a lower house seat.
[Ben Ballingall] obviously you need to get 50% or 40% of the vote.
[Ben Ballingall] It's quite hard.
[Ben Ballingall] But in an upper house seat in federal, call it 4% of the vote.
[Ben Ballingall] Upcoming, more importantly, in the next year, we've got the WA state election.
[Ben Ballingall] And due to some specifics around WA election law, and also, I guess, the strength of micro-parties, our micro-parties in particular, our in WA, we could be looking at something with maybe 2%, 2% to 3%?
[Brian Khuu?] Yep.
[Ben Ballingall] Which, you know, it sounds tiny, but it's a big thing in real politics.
[Ben Ballingall] But it's certainly not crazy anymore.
[Ben Ballingall] 2%, 3%, some sliding, some, you know, strong team-ups with other micro-parties.
[Ben Ballingall] And it wouldn't be crazy to see something come out of this WA state election.
[Ben Ballingall] But obviously I'm always blindly hopeful.
[Brian Khuu] Of course.
[Brian Khuu] I think we're covered pretty much most of what we needed to think about.
[Brian Khuu] But for those who are interested in the Flux system and like maybe, maybe they're from Finland or maybe they're even in Australia, like what's next for them?
[Ben Ballingall] Well, the first thing you can do is reach out, voteflux.org or on Facebook, Instagram, YouTube, LinkedIn, and reach out and get in touch with one of us.
[Ben Ballingall] Other than that, we have a Discord, which is getting there, a couple of few hundred people on our community who can, you know, will fill in a lot of these questions and answers like it doesn't have to be me.
[Ben Ballingall] So discord.io/fluxparty, especially if you're in a country other than Australia, or if you're in Australia, in South Australia, Tasmania, Queensland, or the Northern Territory, please get in touch and we can help you get a party registered in your area.
[Brian Khuu] Well, that definitely sounds exciting.
[Brian Khuu] And I really appreciate that you took your time to come along to have a chat with Designing Open Democracy.
[Ben Ballingall] Well, thank you very much.
[Ben Ballingall] It's been a long time coming, the DoD and Flux collab.
[Ben Ballingall] So I'm glad we got it done, man.
[Brian Khuu] Awesome.
[Brian Khuu] Thanks.